{"tossups": [{"question": "This West Virginia-born Air Force Brigadier General collaborated with Pancho Barnes, who had been a member of the Ninety-Nines. Appointed to the Rogers Commission, this man was given an opportunity for his most celebrated action after Slick Goodlin was rejected for demanding too much money. That action by this man was chronicled in<em> The Right Stuff</em> and was achieved while flying the<em> Glamorous</em> <em>Glennis</em>. For ten points, name this pilot who, aboard a Bell X-1 rocket engine-powered aircraft, became the first human to break the sound barrier.", "answer": "Charles Elwood \u201cChuck\u201d<b> Yeager</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This man\u2019s crew was nearly recalled by Juan Tafur, but the members who chose to stay with this man became known as the \u201cFamous Thirteen.\u201d After an enemy leader threw a Bible to the ground in the face of the priest Valverde, this man captured and ransomed that leader for a room full of gold. This man was victorious at the battle of Cajamarca in modern day Peru. For ten points, name this Spanish conqueror of the Incan Empire.", "answer": "Francisco<b> Pizarro</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "A caricaturist as a young man, this artist was mentored by Eug\u00b4ene Boudin who taught him the \u201cen plein air\u201d technique for which this man became known. In response to regular rejections from the Salon de Paris, this man, along with Renoir, C\u00b4ezanne, and others held a heavily criticized exhibition of their own in 1874, and their movement was given a name from one of this man\u2019s paintings,<em> Impressions: Sunrise</em>. For ten points, name this Impressionist painter of the<em> Water Lilies</em> series.", "answer": "Claude<b> Monet</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {}, {"question": "In one event featuring this sport in Auckland, bombs made of flour were thrown on teams and police beat clowns. A tour of one team in this sport was opposed by the Gleneagles Agreement and the group Halt All Racist Tours, owing to racial discrimination in the country from which the team came. Francois Pienaar led South Africa to win this sport\u2019s 1995 World Cup. The Springboks and All Blacks are teams that play, for ten points, what form of football popular in Commonwealth nations?", "answer": "<b> Rugby</b> Union (accept<b> Rugby league</b>, prompt on \u201cLeague\u201d)", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "This man increased gas taxes to fund highway construction through the Collier Burns Act as Governor of California, a position he held a record three consecutive terms. This man replaced Fred Vinson in his highest position in which this man was succeeded by Warren Burger. For ten points, name this Chief of Justice of the Supreme Court who presided over the cases<em> Miranda v Arizona</em> and<em> Brown v the Board of</em> <em>Education</em>, as well as heading the commission that investigated the death of President Kennedy.", "answer": "Earl<b> Warren</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This city is home to the headquarters of the SAARC and the site of the Pashupatinah Temple. This city\u2019s name derives from a wooden shrine that stood in Durbar Square until it was destroyed by a 2015 earthquake. In 2001, Prince Dipendra carried out a massacre in Narayanhity Royal Palace in this city, which led to the death of ten members of the royal family, including King Birendra. For ten points, name this city, the capital of Nepal.", "answer": "<b> Kathmandu</b> (accept pronunciations with either a \u201ct\u201d or a \u201cth\u201d sound)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "In this city in 1891, over 1,000 people died when the<em> General Slocum</em> caught fire and sank in one of this city\u2019s rivers, a river that the Dutch called the \u201cNorth River.\u201d Sheila Abdus-Salaam served on this city\u2019s Civil Court, the first Muslim woman to serve as a judge in the United States. US Airways Flight 1549 took off from this city, hit several birds, then made a water landing without losing any of the 155 on board. For ten points, name this city whose LaGuardia Airport was the starting site of the \u201cMiracle on the Hudson.\u201d", "answer": "<b> New York</b> City (accept<b> NYC</b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This man criticized the minting of private coin in Ireland in his pamphlet \u201cDrapier\u2019s Letters.\u201d This author criticized the Whig Government for not ending their involvement in the War of Spanish Succession in<em> The Conduct of the Allies</em>. This author of<em> A Tale of the Tub</em> satirically suggested to the Irish people that they should sell their infants to the English to ease economic troubles in<em> A Modest Proposal</em>. For ten points, name this author of<em> Gulliver\u2019s Travels</em>.", "answer": "Jonathan<b> Swift</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "Less than ten miles from Dodge City is a two-mile portion of this route that is the longest portion of it remaining today. Trading caravans on this route had to cross a ferry at Arrow Rock, Missouri. A need to pay off debts caused by the Panic of 1819 led William Becknell to establish this route. Mexican caravans on this trail were often intercepted by U.S. troops in the Mexican-American War. For ten points, name this trail that takes its name from the city in which it ended in New Mexico.", "answer": "<b> Santa Fe</b> Trail", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This leader, who supported George W. Bush\u2019s campaign to invade Iraq, was succeeded by Gordon Brown. For ten points, name this Prime Minister of the UK from 1997 to 2007.", "answer": "Tony<b> Blair</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "That city is today known as Ashkelon and is found in this country.", "answer": "State of<b> Israel</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "This ruler\u2019s reign was the subject of the final book of John Foxe\u2019s<em> Book of Martyrs</em>. This ruler issued the First Statute of Repeal to nullify prior religious laws and burned Hugh Latimer and Nicholas Ridley at the stake. This ruler imprisoned the author of the<em> Book of Common Prayer</em>, Thomas Cranmer, after she succeeded Lady Jane Grey. Known for her violent persecutions of Protestants, for ten points, name this ruler who re-Catholicized England before she was succeeded by Elizabeth I.", "answer": "<b> Mary I</b> (accept<b> Mary Tudor</b>, prompt on \u201cBloody Mary\u201d)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "This man paid $65 to have a photograph with a famous woman he met in Minnesota. Alfred Sully defeated an army in which this man served at the Battle of Killdeer Mountain. This man, who surrendered to David Brotherton at Fort Buford, was offered a job by John Burke that allowed him to meet Annie Oakley. This ally of Chief Gall and performer in<em> Buffalo Bill\u2019s Wild West Show</em> once won a battle fought alongside Crazy Horse during which a \u201cLast Stand\u201d was conducted by George Custer. For ten points, name this chief of the Sioux.", "answer": "<b> Sitting Bull</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>Near the end of this film, one character buries two figurines of the protagonist\u2019s relatives claiming \u201cI will see you again.\u201d This film begins at a battle in Vindobona that occurred during the Twelve Year Campaign. After being taken to Mauretania, the protagonist of this</b> <b>film is given to (+)</b> <b>Proximo. A reenactment of the Battle of Zama sees the protagonist</b> <b>lead his Carthaginian side to victory before revealing himself to the brother of Lucilla. The antagonist of this film kills his father (*)</b> Marcus Aurelius after learning that he is not to be named successor. For ten points, name this 2000 Academy Award winning film in which Russell Crowe stars as Maximus.", "answer": "<em><b> Gladiator</b></em>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "<b>A mining rights concession that this man negotiated with the Matabele king Lobengula paved the way for the creation of a namesake southern African colony. This man supported</b> <b>the Jameson Raid and founded the (+)</b> <b>De Beers diamond company in Kimberley. A</b> <b>cartoon in</b><em><b> Punch</b></em><b> depicted this man as a colossus astride Africa as a result of his advocacy for a (*) </b> railroad spanning the continent from \u201cCape to Cairo.\u201d For ten points, name this Victorian imperialist for whom a prestigious scholarship at Oxford university is named.", "answer": "Cecil (John)<b> Rhodes</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>The Battle of Klushino during this period resulted in a group of seven nobles offering their support for Prince Wladyslaw. Marina Mneszich was appointed queen during this period thanks to an invasion led by (+) Sigismund III of Poland. Three men known as the False Dmitris attempted to claim the throne during this period that began after the death of Feodor led to the end of the (*)</b> Rurik dynasty. For ten points, identify this period of turmoil in Russian history that ended with the coronation of Michael Romanov.", "answer": "<b> Time of Troubles</b> (accept<b> Smuta</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>Henry Gough became known as the \u201chammer\u201d of people of this religion, and the second war against a state named for this religion occurred after Patrick Vans Agnew was sent to</b> <b>take (+)</b> <b>Multan. An empire of this religion contained four provinces, including Peshawar</b> <b>and Lahore. That empire of this religion was created after the misals were united under the \u201cLion of the (*)</b> Punjab,\u201d Maharaja Ranjit Singh. For ten points, name this religion based on the teachings of Guru Nanak, the fifth largest organized religion in the world.", "answer": "<b> Sikh</b>ism (accept<b> Sikh</b>il)", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {"question": "<b>This man served as a New York delegate in opposition to Andrew Jackson\u2019s candidacy in 1828 and was an Anti-Mason when elected to Congress in 1837. Later in this man\u2019s career,</b> <b>he became a (+)</b> <b>\u201cKnow Nothing\u201d and finished third in the U.S. presidential election of</b> <b>1856. As Vice President, this man presided over debates on Henry Clay\u2019s Omnibus Bill and the issue of slavery in the (*) </b> Mexican Cession. For ten points, name this man who advanced the Compromise of 1850, the 13th President of the United States.", "answer": "Millard<b> Fillmore</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>During this battle, the oiler</b><em><b> Neosho</b></em><b> was attacked by Japanese pilots who mistook it for an aircraft carrier. The</b><em><b> Lexington</b></em><b> was severely damaged in this battle that</b> <b>prevented the Japanese invasion of (+)</b> <b>Port Moresby. As the opposing fleets never</b> <b>sighted or directly fired upon each other, this naval battle was the first to be fought with carrier (*)</b> aircraft alone. For ten points, name this May, 1942 naval battle that took place in a namesake sea northeast of Australia.", "answer": "Battle of the<b> Coral Sea</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}